<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://daniel-halpern.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://daniel-halpern.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-03T20:00:57+00:00</updated><id>https://daniel-halpern.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Dry Cleaning Data Science!</title><link href="https://daniel-halpern.github.io/blog/2025/Business-Data-Science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dry Cleaning Data Science!"/><published>2025-12-29T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-29T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://daniel-halpern.github.io/blog/2025/Business-Data-Science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://daniel-halpern.github.io/blog/2025/Business-Data-Science/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[End-to-End Data Science Project to modernize my family's business' decision making from intuition to quantified data science.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From Student to Advisor, Two Summers at ARISE.</title><link href="https://daniel-halpern.github.io/blog/2025/From-Student-to-Advisor-Two-Summers-at-ARISE/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Student to Advisor, Two Summers at ARISE."/><published>2025-10-27T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-27T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://daniel-halpern.github.io/blog/2025/From-Student-to-Advisor-Two-Summers-at-ARISE</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://daniel-halpern.github.io/blog/2025/From-Student-to-Advisor-Two-Summers-at-ARISE/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Note: Names of <strong>students</strong> have been changed to protect privacy. (This does not apply to Professor Neill, Luann, and names in the footer)</em></p> <p>There are two stories of an ambitious high schooler in New York City.</p> <p>The first is the one we all know: the story of the kid with a well-crafted childhood. The one whose discipline is ingrained from hours of private tutoring. The one who carries the heavy weight of expectations, and whose brilliance is defined by their ability to meet them. The one whose high-achieving parents understand the precise, unwritten rules of the academic and social game, unlocking hidden doors that others don’t even know exist.</p> <p>The second story is quieter, but it’s just as powerful. It’s the story of the kid from the city’s outer boroughs. The one juggling work, helping their parents run errands, taking care of siblings, and cooking dinner on top of their academic workload. The one who self-learns through Khan Academy and SAT books from the public library. The one whose academic and career dreams are sparked from words on internet forums instead of scientific lectures at the dinner table.</p> <p>They are often pushing against a headwind of well-meaning, practical resistance from their family and themselves, who urge them to mend their personal financial circumstances by using their time and energy to work instead of training to pursue the luxury of thinking. They have a fanatic desire to fulfill their potential, but have no platform, no connections, and no one to open the first door.</p> <p>I know this story intimately because it was mine. I went into the ARISE application process as that kid, just wanting to escape summers working at the family dry cleaners and the embarrassment of running into my classmates while delivering laundry (I am now grateful for it). I had only a few self-taught Python programs and a head full of dreams of AI from reading from researchers like Melanie Mitchell, Andrej Karpathy, Yann Lecun, and Andrew Ng. My parents, who graduated from middle school in a fishing village in China, couldn’t offer guidance. I just knew I wanted to do <em>something</em> productive and dream big.</p> <p>For a student like me, being passionate, resilient, and decent at academics is not enough. We still won’t be able to compete with the well-sculpted, stellar resume and web of connections of other kids. This is why we don’t just need an <em>opportunity</em>; we need a <em>signal</em>.</p> <p>For me, ARISE was that signal.</p> <p>It was more than just a summer program; it was the first true platform I ever had. Joining Professor Daniel Neill’s Machine Learning For Good Lab, I was immediately exposed to real, high-level research. I was assigned to a project that had stalled. With the generous and amazing mentorship of Professor Neill, I was able to help get it moving again, building a working model and gaining an understanding of its inner workings. It was the first time I saw my passion translate into a tangible result. I still remember the high from Professor Neill’s feedback, “great work in such a short amount of time.”</p> <p>But the most transformative part? The validation. For a random no-name kid, uncertainty is a constant companion. That recommendation letter, that confirmation from a professor that <em>I was good at this</em>, was life-changing. ARISE didn’t just give me skills; it gave me confidence.</p> <p>I would not have ended up at a great university without ARISE. Academic talent means little if you never get a chance to show your passion to someone who can open a door.</p> <p>This past summer, I returned as an advisor, and I learned that ARISE’s impact goes even deeper than the lab work.</p> <p>I saw it in my advisee, Nathan. He reminded me so much of myself – an immigrant from Jamaica, a dream of being an electrical engineering researcher, and a quiet, respectful shyness. (I was, for the first time, “Mr. Zhang”!) In our initial meetings, he was reserved, soft-spoken, and avoided eye contact. But by the end of the summer, I watched that same student confidently presenting his research at the American Museum of Natural History, surrounded by a new group of friends. ARISE gave Nathan, a regular kid with a big dream, an opportunity to shine and a community of like-minded peers to shine with. He has ambitions to obtain a PhD EE.</p> <p>I could see my younger self in many of my students – timid, nervous, but brilliant. I shared my own research struggles, hoping to give them the confidence to be ambitious, to work through the code, and to embrace the uncertainty of research. It was a privilege to watch one advisee, Jonathan, who would physically shake from nervousness in our meetings, go on to present his research confidently in front of a full classroom at the final symposium. He found his own voice. I saw another group, devastated after a tough meeting with their PI, find the resilience within themselves to make a one-week turnaround to build a full, working project. My role was simply to remind them that this uncertainty <em>was</em> the work, and that they were capable.</p> <p>That is the magic of ARISE. It changes the lives of kids with unseen potential, kids who just need a chance to demonstrate their merit.</p> <p>This utility – to recognize and nurture unseen, ambitious talent – is not something you can easily measure on a spreadsheet. The impact isn’t just individual; it’s communal and national. Generosity received teaches generosity that must be practiced for the next generation.</p> <p>ARISE is a signal for all normal, ambitious kids that there is an opportunity for them, that America is not just a society where you get ahead only through connections. It is the embodiment of the American Dream.</p> <p>For this area of impact, only the sky is the limit. I urge the continued support of changing the lives of low-income students.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/ARISE_2025-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/ARISE_2025-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/ARISE_2025-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/ARISE_2025.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <blockquote> <p>Many thanks to Luann William Moore, the director of the ARISE program. Having worked behind the scenes, I now understand the immense effort that goes into running these programs. Luann’s passion and vision, along with her dedicated team, are what made ARISE a great experience. I am also grateful to mentors like Professor Neill, who are willing to offer their mentorship to high school students. Finally, I want to thank the Pinkerton Foundation for making this all possible.</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Thank you Celine Cotran for reading the drafts of this entry.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ideas"/><category term="opinions"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On high school research oppurtunities.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to get into college</title><link href="https://daniel-halpern.github.io/blog/2024/How-to-get-into-college/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to get into college"/><published>2024-07-11T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-11T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://daniel-halpern.github.io/blog/2024/How-to-get-into-college</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://daniel-halpern.github.io/blog/2024/How-to-get-into-college/"><![CDATA[<p>Thank you so much to <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/xinjie-tina-zeng/">Tina Zeng</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/daniel-halpern-424739264/">Daniel Halpern</a> for reviewing this post.</p> <p>To my lowerclassmen friends at ERHS…</p> <h2 id="who-am-i-and-who-is-this-for">Who am I and who is this for?</h2> <p>My name is Ryan and I am a first-generation, low-income student from Eleanor Roosevelt High School in NYC. I am attending Columbia University for my undergraduate degree in Computer Science. This post is a collection of thoughts that I think are helpful to having a good high school career and a successful college application. I particularly hope this post can help young students (8th graders, freshmen, sophomores, juniors) who are from a similar background as me achieve their academic goals. These thoughts are a hodge podge of anecdotal insights, advice, intuitions, and opinions of mine so take everything as you will. The blog also includes insights from Tina Zeng, someone who I deeply respect and is now an undergrad at Yale University.</p> <p>Here are all the schools I applied to and the result:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Rejected</th> <th>Waitlisted</th> <th>Accepted</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Stanford (Deferred)</td> <td>Princeton</td> <td>Columbia (John Jay Scholar)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Yale</td> <td>Carnegie Mellon University</td> <td>Cornell</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Upenn</td> <td>Rice</td> <td>Johns Hopkins</td> </tr> <tr> <td>NYU</td> <td>University of Washington St Louis</td> <td>Georgetown</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td>Vanderbilt</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td>Williams College</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td>GIT (CS)</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td>University Of Virginia (Rodman Scholar)</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td>Macaulay Honors College</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td>Stonybrook (Honors)</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <h2 id="cultivate-a-strong-mindset-8th-graderfreshman">Cultivate a Strong Mindset (8th grader/Freshman)</h2> <p>Your mindset is probably the most important thing to get right as everything else will naturally fall in place afterward (i.e. motivation, work, and personality). This is not groundbreaking advice but have a growth mindset, be active, do things, and think about the long term. If you are a freshman taking the time to read this then I imagine you are already a go-getter; keep doing what you are doing. The first thing you must know about getting into college is that you CAN get into a great college. You don’t need to be a founder of a Fortune 500 company or win International Olympiads. What you do need is agency, independence, resiliency, intellectual curiosity, and an entrepreneurial spirit. In addition, one trait that is often undervalued is being a good person; someone who cares about humanity and truly believes in their ideas. I think there are numerous benefits to being a good person including better mental health and deeper connections with other humans. Humans are naturally drawn to helping other good humans.</p> <h2 id="develop-beliefs-freshmansophomore">Develop Beliefs (Freshman/Sophomore)</h2> <p>Develop good, interesting, and nuanced ideas. It’s incredible how in modern society we can just freely listen to the smartest people in the world and have the freedom to adopt their ideas. You can be much more certain that if a smart person has thought long and hard about a subject then their ideas will have merit in them. This doesn’t mean the beliefs are guaranteed to be right or that your beliefs have to be right. Determining what is right is wrong is intuitively simple but difficult when applied, just pick and choose what you think is most right and always be open-minded to new ideas. For me, I thought developing strong beliefs and ideas was critical in helping me land extracurricular activities that led to strong compounding growth as I met more interesting people to discuss with. Here are some of the people who influenced the way I think: Melanie Mitchell, Andrej Karpathy, Henry Kissinger, Lee Kuan Yew, 80,000 hours, Andrew Ng, Yann LeCun, etc.</p> <h2 id="extra-curricular-activities-sophomorejunior">Extra Curricular Activities (Sophomore/Junior)</h2> <p>There are so many free programs out there that want to help students like YOU. You are their target. However, prestigious programs are very selective so view this opportunity as a trial run for the college application process. Be ambitious and apply widely. As you are writing your essays, start deeply reflecting on what you might want to do in the future and the stories that made you who you are. If you are in NYC, the specialized high schools have a great database of opportunities. Some programs I joined were: ARISE NYU, Young Ambassador @ EFL Stern, and Civics Unplugged’s Digital Citizen Fellowship.</p> <p>There are also so many great organizations out there like: Girls Who Code, AI4ALL, Google’s Code Next, etc. Take advantage of all of them.</p> <blockquote> <p>Thoughts from Tina:</p> </blockquote> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>“Think about program acceptances as a feedback loop. In addition, don't feel pigeonholed in only applying to programs you have some background in -- often if you can articulate why you want to participate in a program that you have no previous experience in, you'll be fine. In the future, if you want to do more activities related to those programs, it'll be easier.”
</code></pre></div></div> <h2 id="exploring-interests">Exploring Interests</h2> <p>As you start to develop ideas, don’t pigeonhole yourself into activities. Take the time to explore. For me, I was interested in photography, filmmaking, economics, history, rock climbing, and AI.</p> <h2 id="fit-is-extremely-important">Fit is extremely important</h2> <p>Each school, organization, and institution has its own culture, strengths, and passions. Most students underrate the importance of understanding these aspects of the schools they are applying to. My experience applying to Georgetown really solidified my thoughts on this. Even though I felt like I did not have the “best” essays for Georgetown, I believe what got me in was my incredible conversation about policy with my interviewer and how aligned my career goals were to initiatives at Georgetown like CSET. While I am unfortunately not able to attend Georgetown due to financial reasons, I hope to cross paths with the university in the future. Another example is Columbia, a school that truly prides itself in its Core Curriculum. If you can appreciate and understand why the University believes in it so much and how you can grow from being part of it, then it is likely your chances of getting in would increase (make sure to mention the Core Curriculum in your Columbia essays).</p> <h2 id="recommendation-letterscompetitions">Recommendation Letters/Competitions</h2> <p>I view these elements of the application as just stamps of confirmation to decrease the uncertainty the admission officers may have of you: recommendation letters are a confirmation of your character and competitions are a confirmation of your skills. Letter of recommendations are one of the most underrated parts of the application – don’t make this mistake.</p> <p>I think Karpathy has good ideas on recommendation letters (go to references, references, references): <a href="https://karpathy.github.io/2016/09/07/phd/">A Survival Guide to a PhD</a> (karpathy.github.io)</p> <h2 id="testing-satgrades">Testing (SAT)/Grades</h2> <p>I’m going to make this simple for you. Use Khan Academy’s SAT prep. Then just try your best on the test. You really don’t have to spend money on anything, only time and effort. Test scores are just one part of your application.</p> <p>Kartpathy also has good ideas on doing well: <a href="https://cs.stanford.edu/people/karpathy/advice.html">Andrej’s advice for success</a> (stanford.edu)</p> <h2 id="concluding-thoughts">Concluding thoughts</h2> <p>These are just thoughts that I believe helped me but that doesn’t necessarily mean they will help you. There is no right way of doing anything and everybody’s story is different. Furthermore, there is just so much luck involved and maybe some black magic happening in the background…[I have this theory that counselors are doing selective nudges in the background, but I cannot confirm. I promise I am not a conspiracy theorist]. I think as long as you are thinking, moving, failing, and improving, you will do great. Good luck and enjoy the journey!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ideas"/><category term="opinions"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Anecdotal advice for HS underclassmen]]></summary></entry></feed>